Finding Aid for Eunice Burns papers, 1960-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Eunice Burns papers 1960-2011
Burns, Eunice.
3.5 linear feet
85476 Aa 2
Democratic member of the Ann Arbor City Council (Mich.); also member of the Ann Arbor Planning Commission, the Ann Arbor Development Authority, and the Huron River Watershed Council. The collection includes correspondence, reports, minutes, and other materials largely concerning her organizational activities.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This collection was donated by Eunice L. Burns (Donor No. 4738 ) in multiple accessions beginning in 1979.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Eunice L. Burns has been active in Ann Arbor civic and community affairs and city politics since the mid-1950s. For more than four decades, she has been a keen observer and sometime participant in Ann Arbor city government. Beginning first with her involvement in the revision of Ann Arbor's city charter in 1955, Burns went on in local politics with her successful campaign in 1962 for a seat on the Ann Arbor City Council. While on council, Burns's principal interests were in the areas of civil rights and city planning. She was a strong advocate for the landmark Ann Arbor Fair Housing Ordinance which was enacted on September 16, 1963.
Burns was re-elected to her council seat in 1964 and again in 1966. In 1965, in the midst of her second term on council, Burns decided to run for mayor. Hoping to be the first woman mayor and the first Democratic mayor elected since 1957, Burns lost to incumbent Republican Wendell Hulcher by more than three thousand votes. Despite her defeat, she continued to represent the first ward on council for another three years. In 1968, she decided against running for a fourth term, choosing instead to become a member of the Ann Arbor Planning Commission. She served on the commission until June 1974, serving as chair of the commission from May 1970 to August 1971.
Before coming to Ann Arbor, Burns had received her BS degree from Wisconsin State College and had done graduate work at the University of Wisconsin and New York University. In 1967, she began pursuing her Master's degree in the political science department at the University of Michigan. Specializing in urban planning, she received her Master's in 1970. Burns became Assistant Dean of the School of Education at the University of Michigan in the 1970s. When, in 1973, Marcia Federbush filed a complaint with the University of Michigan Athletic Department listing 125 instances where women athletes were treated unfairly, Burns was asked by U-M President Robben Fleming to chair the Committee for Study of Intercollegiate Athletics for Women. Burns, with the rest of the committee, did a survey of programs at other large universities, collected testimony from Michigan women athletes, and issued a report.
In 1980, Burns was elected vice-chair of the Huron Watershed Council. She has also been active in Ann Arbor's Downtown Development Authority (DDA) since 1979.
The Eunice L. Burns collection primarily documents her activities in Ann Arbor government. The collection has been divided into five series: Ann Arbor City Council, 1962-68; Ann Arbor Planning Commission, 1968-74, University of Michigan Committee to Study Intercollegiate Athletics for Women, 1971-76; Downtown Development Authority, 1979-90; Huron River Watershed Council; and Miscellaneous.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Ann Arbor (Mich.). Common Council.; Ann Arbor (Mich.). Downtown Development Authority.; Ann Arbor (Mich.). Planning Commission.; Civil rights--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Discrimination in housing--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Huron River Watershed Council.; Municipal government--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Committee to Study Intercollegiate Athletics for Women.; University of Michigan--Sports.; Women's rights--Michigan.; Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Students.; Women in politics--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
- Ann Arbor City Council 1962-1988
  Ann Arbor City Council, the largest series in the collection, concerns municipal government issues during the turbulent 1960s in addition to some material in the 1970s and 1980s as well. Of greatest significance perhaps was the city-wide debate over a fair housing ordinance. Burns's involvement in this issue is documented in this series as well as the involvement of citizens and groups such as CORE and the NAACP. Civil rights issues are also addressed in the following folders: Police, Human Rights, and the Human Relations Committee. Other issues documented in this series include Ann Arbor's physical growth and such related areas as water, parking, and the maintenance and improvement of various public services. Furthermore, information on candidates and election returns, materials handed out to precinct workers, and mayoral campaign material and speeches are included.
  - Airport (Municipal) 1963 (Box 1)
  - Annexation and Growth 1962-1972 (Box 1)
  - Annexation and Growth 1971 (Box 1)
  - Billboards and Signs Ordinance 1965-1968 (Box 1)
  - Black Pond Development Dispute 1968-1969 (Box 1)
  - Board of Supervisors Appointments 1963 (Box 1)
  - Candidates 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - Central Business District 1961-1965 (Box 1)
  - Charter Amendment Committee 1962-1967 (Box 1)
  - Civic Center Committee 1969 (Box 1)
  - Civil Rights 1962-1964 (Box 1)
  - Commercial Development and Zoning Statistics (Ann Arbor and Ypsilanti Area) 1963 (Box 1)
  - Community Center 1964 (Box 1)
  - Community College 1962-1964 (Box 1)
  - Community Goals Committee 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - Constituent Relations (Box 1)
  - Date for City Elections 1964 (Box 1)
  - Democrats-Toasts (Box 1)
  - Direct Aid vs. ADC-U 1963 (Box 1)
  - Election Materials 1962-1969 (Box 1)
  - Election Returns 1952-1988 (Box 1)
  - Elm Spray 1965-1968 (Box 1)
  - Employment Opportunities Act Proposed Program 1965 (Box 1)
  - Fair Housing
    - 1962 (Box 1)
    - 1963 (Box 1)
    - Petition 1963 (Box 1)
    - 1964 (Box 1)
    - 1965 (Box 1)
  - Fair Housing Ordinance Amendment 1965 (Box 1)
  - (Blue Ribbon) Finance Committee 1967, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - (Blue Ribbon) Finance Committee 1968 (Box 1)
  - (Blue Ribbon) Finance Committee 1969 (Box 1)
  - Garden Club 1965 (Box 1)
  - Greenbelt 1965 (Box 1)
  - High-rise development and Parking 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - Historical Commission 1962-1967 (Box 1)
  - Hotel (Washington and Fourth) 1963 (Box 1)
  - Housing 1966-1974 (Box 1)
  - Housing: Multiple Family Units 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - Housing: Public 1964-1967 (Box 1)
  - Housing: Voluntary Rehabilitation 1960-1962 (Box 1)
  - Human Relations 1963-1968 (Box 1)
  - Human Rights Commission 1960-1967 (Box 1)
  - Huron River 1967-1970 (Box 1)
  - Huron Parkway 1967 (Box 1)
  - Huron Valley Development/Preservation 1965 (Box 1)
  - Mayoral Campaign 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - Literature and General Materials 1961-1968 (Box 1)
  - Nature Trails 1964 (Box 1)
  - Northside Baptist Church Rezoning Matter 1963 (Box 1)
  - Northside Planning Committee 1967 (Box 1)
  - Parking 1962-1966 (Box 1)
  - Parks and Natural Areas 1962-1972 (Box 1)
  - Parks: Swimming Pools and Skating Rinks 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - Plymouth-Barton Overpass 1961 (Box 1)
  - Police 1962-1966 (Box 1)
  - Precinct Worker Materials 1960-1964 (Box 1)
  - Publicity 1963 (Box 1)
  - Refuse Collections 1963-1965 (Box 1)
  - Shelter Program Protest Letter to President Kennedy circa 1963 (Box 1)
  - Speeches (Box 1)
  - Staebler Papers 1963 (Box 2)
  - Summary of Ann Arbor 1965-1966 (Box 2)
  - Taxes (City Income) 1965-1966 (Box 2)
  - Teen Center 1967 (Box 2)
  - Utilities 1962-1964 (Box 2)
  - Vietnam 1966-1967 (Box 2)
  - Wards (First Ward) 1963 (Box 2)
  - Washtenaw Neighborhood Group (Box 2)
  - Water Supply Issues 1963-1971 (Box 2)
  - Women's International League for Peace and Freedom (Ann Arbor-Ypsilanti Branch) 1963 (Box 2)
  - Youth Services (Box 2)
  - Zoning 1964-1966 (Box 2)
  - Zoo in Ann Arbor 1962 (Box 2)
- Ann Arbor Planning Commission 1961-1974
  The Ann Arbor Planning Commission series documents the activities of Burns as chairman and member of the planning commission and relates to physical changes proposed for the city.
  - Ann Arbor Public Schools: Building/Site Issues 1974 (Box 2)
  - Bird Hills Park 1968 (Box 2)
  - Briarwood 1970-1972 (Box 2)
  - Capital Improvements 1967-1979 (Box 2)
  - Central Area 1972-1974 (Box 2)
  - Citizen's Association for Central Planning 1971-1971 (Box 2)
  - Construction Statistics 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - Design Review Working Committee 1970-1973 (Box 2)
  - Environmental Interpretive Center 1968-1969 (Box 2)
  - First Apostolic Church 1971 (Box 2)
  - Garden Homes Association 1970-1973 (Box 2)
  - General Development Plans 1966-1973 (Box 2)
  - Grants to Ann Arbor 1972 (Box 2)
  - "Guide for Change" circa 1970s (Box 2)
  - Historical Architecture 1971-1972 (Box 2)
  - Isberg-Courtelis-Abbott Zoning Petition (Black Pond Development Dispute) 1968 (Box 2)
  - League of Women Voters 1967-1979 (Box 2)
  - Neighborhood Analyses circa 1970s (Box 2)
  - North Central Area circa 1970 (Box 2)
  - North East Area 1974 (Box 2)
  - North West Area 1971-1972 (Box 2)
  - Packard Road Development (Packard/Platt Plaza) 1972 (Box 2)
  - Planning Commission
    - Appointments (Women) 1972 (Box 2)
    - By-laws and Procedures (Box 2)
    - Correspondence 1969-1971 (Box 2)
    - Clippings 1968-1974 (Box 2)
    - General 1967-1971 (Box 2)
    - Letters to the Editor (Ann Arbor News), 1970 (Box 2)
  - Rent Control 1974 (Box 2)
  - Riverside Village 1973 (Box 2)
  - St. Joseph Mercy Hospital Annexation 1971 (Box 2)
  - Scio Township Planning Commission 1971 (Box 2)
  - Sister Lakes 1974 (Box 2)
  - South Area 1973 (Box 2)
  - South-Southwest Area Study 1971 (Box 2)
  - Subdivision Control 1971 (Box 2)
  - Waste Treatment Problems 1971 (Box 2)
  - Zoning Proposals 1971-1973 (Box 2)
- University Of Michigan Committee to Study Intercollegiate Sports for Women 1970-1976
  In 1973 Burns was asked to chair the University of Michigan Committee to Study Intercollegiate Sports for Women. Files from this work include memos and correspondence, minutes of meetings and a report of the committee.
  - History 1970-1973 (Box 2)
  - Memos and Correspondence 1973-1974 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous 1973 (Box 2)
  - Minutes June 29, 1973-October 4, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Notes July-October 1973 (Box 2)
  - Report and Report Drafts 1973 (Box 2)
  - State of Michigan Association for Intercollegiate Athletics for Women 1973-1976 (Box 2)
- Downtown Development Authority (DDA) 1979-1990
  Act 197 of the Public Acts of 1975 provides for the establishment of Downtown Development Authorities. DDAs have the purpose to assist in the restoration of downtown districts of communities. Burns's involvement in the DDA is documented in this series.
  - Ann/Ashley Bond Issue 1986 (Box 2)
  - Annual Reports 1984-1986 (Box 2)
  - Ashley Plaza 1987 (Box 2)
  - Budget Summaries 1983-1987 (Box 2)
  - By-laws and Membership 1985-1987 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1981-1988 (Box 2)
  - Development/Planning circa 1986 (Box 2)
  - Downtown Historic District Study Committee 1988 (Box 3)
  - History of DDA(notes) (Box 3)
  - Main Street News Network 1987 (Box 3)
  - Meetings, Agendas, Minutes, Notes
    - 1984 (Box 3)
    - 1985 (Box 3)
    - 1986 (Box 3)
    - 1987 (Box 3)
    - 1988 (Box 3)
    - 1989, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - 1990 (Box 3)
  - Memos (Box 3)
  - Notes (Box 3)
  - Report to the Michigan Legislature March 31, 1979 (Box 3)
  - Resolutions 1982-1987 (Box 3)
  - Taxes, Increment Plans 1982-1986 (Box 3)
  - Traffic Study August 1986 (Box 3)
  - William and First Committee 1986-1987 (Box 3)
- Huron River Watershed Council
  The Huron River Watershed Council files largely documents the annual Huron River Day celebration. There are also published and collected materials relating to the protection of the Huron River Watershed.
  - History and background material (Box 3)
    (include 30th anniversary celebration)
  - Huron River Day
    - General
      - 1980-1983 (Box 3)
      - 1985-1989 (Box 3)
      - 1990-1993 (Box 3)
    - Clippings (Box 3)
    - Comcast (proposed sponsorship) (Box 3)
    - Proclamations / Programs 1980-2001 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Wetlands issue (Box 3)
  - State of the Huron Conference 2003, 2005, and 2008 (Box 3)
  - Board of Directors / Executive Committee materials 1993-2011, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Publications and miscellaneous, 4 folders (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous series concerns Burns's activities with the Ann Arbor Democratic Committee. There are also articles and speeches and papers she wrote while studying for his master's degree in politics science at the University of Michigan.
  - Ann Arbor Democratic Committee 1960-1969
    - General Materials 1960-1965 (Box 4)
    - Platform Materials 1960-1969 (Box 4)
  - Letters, received (invitations, thank you letters) 1966-1980 (Box 4)
  - Articles written 1966-1977 (Box 4)
  - Master's Papers and Projects (in Political Science at The University of Michigan) 1967-1970 (Box 4)